CV — Joshua Bowles

Contact Information

Company One On One Marketing

2912 Executive Pkwy,

Suite 300, Lehi, UT 84043

Mail bowlesling@gmail.com, jbowles@1on1.com

Web jbowles

Overall Experience

since 2010 Research and software development in business

since 2007 Research in mathematical, biological, and documentary linguistics

since 2012 Research and software development in applications using big data sets and

machine learning techniques for text processing; currently working on how to deliver near real-time results for large data analysis (for example, near

real-time twitter stream with text classification).

Employment

2010 – present **Software Developer and Researcher**, One On One Marketing

Internet Marketing Company, Lehi, UT,

Develop and mantain in-house products with Ruby and Rails; use of OLTP and OLAP architectures, familiar with formal research in search engine marketing,

2008 – 2010 Adjunct Lecturer, Department of English

Utah Valley University, Orem, UT.

Research techniques, informal logic, and pragmatics relevant to science compo-

sition.

2009, July – Nov Computational Linguist (Intern), Attensity Corporation

U.S. Technology Center, Salt Lake City, UT.

Knowledge engineering; named entity recognition; compiling and judging corpora of lexical items designed to fit within specific ontologies; some work on developing methods for introducing fixed phrases and idioms into the lexicon.

Education

Present PhD on hold

2006–2008 University of Utah

M.A., Theoretical Linguistics Thesis: *Agreement in Tuyuca* Advisor: Lyle Campbell

2000–2006 Metropolitan State College of Denver

B.A., English (minor in Linguistics)

Thesis: *Dislocated Poetics* Advisor: Paul Farkas

Research

General Computational and Theoretical Linguistics, Software Development, Data

Storage

Linguistic Evidentiality, Idioms & Polysemy, Modality, Tense, Context

Other Logic, Probability, Algebra, Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning

Projects on Hold Polysemy and Context, What is Computational Rhetoric?, Recursion in Lan-

guage; Symmetry in X-bar Structure; Syntax and Pragmatics of Evidentiality in

English; English Corpus of Evidentiality Data

Programming Languages

Most Experience Ruby

Actively Learning Node.js, C, Python, Lisp, Java

(in order of importance)

Data Storage

Most Experience MySQL

Actively Learning PostgreSQL, Hadoop (and Hive)

Limited MongoDB, Redis, Oracle

(in order of proficiency)

Other Technologies

Markup ETEX, HTML

Query Languages SQL, Javascript, PL/SQL (limited)

Tools Emacs, Vim, Oracle Application Express

Platforms Linux (Ubuntu, Fedora, Arch, CentOS), Mac OSX, Windows

Other Apache, WebSocket & TCP

Publications

The morphosyntax of tense-evidentials: An initial model. LSO Working Papers

in Linguistics: Proceedings of the 6th Workshop in General Linguistics, Volume 8.

University of Wisconsin-Madison.

2009 The Eastern Tukanoan languages and the typology of classifiers. *Proceedings of*

the 33rd Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistics Society. (Wilson Silva and

Joshua Bowles)

2009 Review of Heck (2008), On pied-piping: Wh-movement and beyond (Mouton de

Gruyter). LinguistList.

2008 Some questions about determining causal inference and criteria for evidence:

Response to Ladd, Dediu, and Kinsella (2008). Biolinguistics 2.2-3: 247-255.

2007

Review of Niyogi (2006), *The computational nature of language learning and evolution* (MIT Press). *Word* 57.2: 178-183. (pre-published version here)

submitted

Notice of Booij (2007), *The grammar of words* (Oxford University Press). eLanguage.

Notice of Schäfer (2008), *The syntax of (anti-)causatives: External arguments in change-of-state contexts* (Amsterdam: John Benjamins). eLanguage.

Language families. *Encyclopedia of Native American History* ed. by Peter C.Mancall. New York: Facts on File. (see submitted draft here)

Linguistic areas. *Encyclopedia of Native American History* ed. by Peter C. Mancall. New York: Facts on File. (see submitted draft here)

Talks & Conferences

2008

Evidentials, Agreement, and Tuyuca: Initial Hypotheses. *Linguistics Department Student Conference* 7, University of Utah, April 10.

Evidentiality and Agreement Interactions in Tuyuca: A Generative Approach. *Workshop in General Linguistics* 6, University of Wisconsin-Madison, April 4-5.

Agreement and Tense-Evidentiality Morphs in Tuyuca. *Workshop on Structure and Constituency in the Languages of the Americas* 13, Queens University, Ontario, Canada, March 28-30 (unable to attend).

The "Language of Observation" in Linguistics (Informal Presentation). University of Utah Linguistics Reading Group, February 15.

2007

Neural correlates of Grammatical Gender: Functionalist and Formalist Assumptions (Informal Presentation). University of Utah Linguistics Reading Group, October 15.

Classifiers and Typology in Eastern Tukanoan Languages. *7th Biennial Meeting of the Association for Linguistic Typology*, Paris, France, September 25-28. (Wilson Silva and Joshua Bowles)

Formalism and Functionalism in Language Documentation. *Department of Foreign Languages and Literatures*, Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Brazil, June 10.

The Amazonian Languages Research and Documentation Group. Poster. *3rd Annual Conference on Endangered Languages and Cultures of the Native Americas*, University of Utah, April 13-15. (Wilson Silva and Joshua Bowles)

The Eastern Tukanoan Languages and the Typology of Classifiers. *33rd Annual Berkeley Linguistics Society Conference*, University of Berkeley, California, February 9-11. (Wilson Silva and Joshua Bowles)

A Typology of Nominal Classifiers in the Eastern Tukanoan Languages. *Department of Linguistics Speakers Series*, University of Utah, January 24. (Wilson Silva and Joshua Bowles)

2004

Neurobiology, Poetry, and Dislocation. *English Faculty Colloquium*, Metropolitan State College of Denver, Colorado, April 25. (Paul Farkas and Joshua Bowles)

2002 Philosophy of Language, the Dialectic Method, and James Joyce. *Honors*

Regional Conference, University of Colorado, Boulder, March 24-25.

Teaching

2010/2008 Science & Technology Writing and Research ENG 2020, Undergraduate

Utah Valley University (9 courses total)

Summer 2009 Humanities & Social Science Writing and Research ENG 2010, Undergraduate

Utah Valley University

Introduction to Composition ENG 1010, Undergraduate

Utah Valley University

Spring 2008/2007 Teaching Assistant, Introduction to Language LING 1200, Undergraduate

University of Utah, David Iannucci (1 semester), Mauricio Mixco (2 semesters)

Fall 2006 Teaching Assistant, Cross-cultural Communication LING 3600, Undergraduate

University of Utah, Stephen Sternfeld

Natural Languages

English (native), Spanish (basic speaking and reading), Portuguese (basic reading, beginning speaking), German and Old English (1 year formal study

each), Tuyuca (structural and research knowledge)

Field Work

2007, May-August Sao Gabriel da Cachoeria and Camanaus, Brazil. Work on all grammatical

aspects of Desano and limited work on Cubeo; Tukanoan family — 4 months.

2004, September Denver, Colorado, USA. Limited work on phonology of Afghani Poshtun; Indo-

Iranian family — 1 month.

Grants

2007 Endangered Language Fund (Co-PI) — \$3,500

2007 International Field Work Travel Funds, University of Utah — \$300

Services

2007-2008 Volunteer work for Conference on Endangered Languages and Cultures of the

North Americas, University of Utah.

2007 Attended by invitation with Wilson Silva the 20th Anniversary Meeting of

FOIRN (Federação das Organizações Indigenas do Rio Negro) Taracua, Brazil:

June 25-29.

2006 Co-founding member of research group: Amazonian Languages Research and

Documentation, Center for American Indian Languages, University of Utah.

2003 Lead student organizer and introductory comments for "Noam Chomsky: live at

the Auraria Campus," Presented by MSCD Student Activities, Denver, Colorado,

April 04.